A Guide to the Photographs, Series 1011-1081 FA438
Rockefeller Archive Center
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA), 1946-1968, n.d.; 1027; 6.2 Cubic Feet 19 boxes.
  - Venezuela, 4
    - PESCA, Prints: 37 (Box 15, Folder 258)
      82. Fishermen take on ice, manufactured in the PESCA Puerto La Cruz plant, at the company's 500-foot pier. 83. Fishermen take on ice, manufactured in the PESCA Puerto La Cruz plant, at the company's 500-foot pier. 84. Discussing the prospects of the reorganized PESCA are (left to right) Merrill Henry of the New York office; Otto Ludwig, plant engineer; Bill Warner, PESCA manager; and John Camp, director of the AIA in VE. 85. Ice, manufactured at the PESCA plant in Puerto La Cruz, is stored in a refrigerated chamber. 86. Ice, manufactured at the PESCA plant in Puerto La Cruz, is stored in a refrigerated chamber. 87. A crowd is gathered on PESCA's 500-foot pier to watch fishing vessels come in to sell their produce and/or buy ice, manufactured at the plant. At the time it was constructed in 1947, this pier was the only such installation east of La Guaira. 88. A crowd is gathered on PESCA's 500-foot pier to watch fishing vessels come in to sell their produce and/or buy ice, manufactured at the plant. At the time it was constructed in 1947, this pier was the only such installation east of La Guaira. 89. One of the largest basic industries of Puerto La Cruz is the manufacture of cement at this plant in Pertegalete. The port also has a fairly heavy shipping schedule and, most important, the largest refineries in the East are located just east of the city. 90. Some fishing vessels can anchor at the PESCA pier to take on their own supply of ice; others are too large and must be supplied by small vessels which operate between the pier and the larger boats of the fishing fleet. 91. Basic construction is almost complete on the new supermarket "CADA," wholly-owned subsidiary of PESCA located in Puerto La Cruz's first shopping center, the project of a local contractor, Jack Goebel. 92. The PESCA plant has been remodeled to accommodate the combining of its operations with those of the former CADA wholesale warehouse, also in Puerto La Cruz. 93. IBEC is opening a new supermarket, CADA, in the space to the rear left of this, Puerto La Cruz's first shopping center. 94. IBEC is opening a new supermarket, CADA, in the space to the rear left of this, Puerto La Cruz's first shopping center. 95. Basic construction is almost complete on the new supermarket CADA, wholly-owned subsidiary of PESCA located in Puerto La Cruz's first shopping center, the project of a local contractor, Jack Goebel. 96. Warehouse merchandise is securely guarded behind wire netting. This "cage" was constructed in the central area of the PESCA plant, a space which has been little utilized for the past few years. 97. Frozen foods and perishables, as well as some of the fish fillets, seafood and beef cuts frozen and packaged by PESCA, are stored in this refrigerated chamber. Frozen whole fish are stores in a refrigerated room next door. 98. Ample space if provided by the large PESCA plant to accommodate the wholesale goods formerly handled by CADA and, latterly, by the IBEC Merchandising Co. 99. Ample space if provided by the large PESCA plant to accommodate the wholesale goods formerly handled by CADA and, latterly, by the IBEC Merchandising Co. 100. The clerical staff for all PESCA operations does business in this office at the plant on the waterfront. 101. One of the largest basic industries of Puerto La Cruz is the manufacture of cement at this plant in Pertegalete. The port also has a fairly heavy shipping schedule and, most important, the largest refineries in the East are located just east of the city. 102. Fisherman take on ice, manufactured in the PESCA plant at the company's 500 foot pier. 103. Fisherman take on ice, manufactured in the PESCA plant at the company's 500 foot pier. 104. The PESCA plant. 105. IBEC is opening a new supermarket, CADA, in the space to the rear left of this, Puerto La Cruz's first shopping center. 106. Discussing the prospects of the reorganized PESCA are (left to right) Merrill Henry of the New York office; Otto Ludwig, plant engineer; Bill Warner, PESCA manager; and John Camp, director of AIA in VE. 107. A truck of PESCA prepares to take on a load of fish at the port of La Guaira, VE, for the overland trip to Caracas, an hour away. PESCA was formed by VBEC to develop commercial fishing in Venezuelan waters. 108. Fishermen take on ice supply at PESCA at Puerto La Cruz. 109. No caption. 110. Fishermen take on ice supply at PESCA at Puerto La Cruz. 111. Fishermen take on ice supply at PESCA at Puerto La Cruz. 112. Fishermen take on ice supply at PESCA at Puerto La Cruz. 113. Fish is laid out for freezing. 114. PESCA plant at Puerto La Cruz has capacity to store 400 tons of frozen fish. 115. PESCA plant at Puerto La Cruz has capacity to store 400 tons of frozen fish. 116. No caption. 117. No caption. 118. No caption.
    - VBEC, Caracas Flood, 1949, Prints: 22 (Box 15, Folder 259)
    - VBEC, Miscellaneous, Prints: 9 (Box 15, Folder 260)
      23. Maracaibo Lake dockside, with products brought from farms about the shore, is one of the most colorful sites (and sights) in Venezuela. 24. VBEC staff and personnel Christmas party, December 23, 1950 - Mr. Van Wagner gives a gift to VBEC's mascot Marimeche, the janitor's daughter. 25. VBEC staff and personnel Christmas party, December 23, 1950 - The organizing committee with Mr. Van Wagner. 26. VBEC staff and personnel Christmas party, December 23, 1950 - Christmas tree with presents which were exchanged among personnel. 27. VBEC staff and personnel Christmas party, December 23, 1950 - The dance at the party. 28. The signing of the option for the leasing of the farm "Central Bolivar" which is situated in Distrito Colon, State of Zulia. The act took place in the VBEC offices in Caracas. From left to right (standing): William F. Coles, Ted Watson, Ray G. Johnson, John R. Camp, and Arturo Brillenbourg, son of Mr. Joaquin Brillenbourg (seated) who is putting his signature at the bottom of the document. (PACA) 29. No caption. 30. From left to right - opening, La Vega Supermarket: 1. ? 2. B. Jofre, IBEC V.P. 3. John Camp 4. Alfredo Izaguirre, CADA Planning 5. Ernest Hawkinson, CADA Public Relations 6. Antonio Saloa, CADA. 31. Opening La Vega Supermarket: 3. A. Izaguirre, CADA 4. John Camp 5. B. Jofre 6. E.A. Hawkinson 7. A. Saloa.
    - VBEC, Monthly Progress Report, 10/15/1949, Prints: 41 (Box 15, Folder 261)
      32. INLACA satisfied customer. 33. Pesquerias Caribe's fish and ice plant located at far end of Los Cocos Bay. 34. Central passageway in CADA's new Caracas warehouse opens onto individual cold-storage compartments. 35. Built-in pulley allows easy transportation of meat and other heavy produce within CADA warehouse. 36. Deep freezer unit is kept at five degrees below zero. 37. CADA's 22,000 sq. ft. cold-storage space in Caracas warehouse will help stabilize perishable foods market. 38. At Agua Blanca farm "Fordraulic" loader collects sand and gravel for house building. 39. Gravel is loaded on trucks to be moved to block construction site. 40. Gravel is unloaded at concrete block making unit. 41. Blocks are turned out at rate of one per minute. 42. Construction of houses began Jan. 1949. 43. Seven 5-room houses went up for livestock caretakers, shop mechanics, and farm foremen and their families. 44. Construction started on two large dormitories with capacity to quarter total of forty single workers. 45. Modern bath facilities and a large kitchen were constructed near workers' dormitories. 46. T-shape structure of manager's house on Agua Blanca allows many windows to offset region's warm climate. 47. Cattle foreman Ramon Oliveros and his family moved into their new five-room bungalow in April 1949. 48. New houses equipped with electricity and running water mean more pleasant and healthful home life for workers. 49. Thatched worker's hut torn down on Agua Blanca last year contrasts sharply with clean, white bungalows. 50. Fisherman disembarks catch at Puerto La Cruz dock where picked up by PCCA truck and hauled to plant. 51. Fish is weighed in at front platform at PCCA plant. 52. Fish is brought into plant for cleaning and processing. 53. Fish to be marketed fresh instead of frozen is stores in plant ice boxes which have total 15 ton capacity. 54. Plant personnel don sheep-lined hooded jackets before entering 40 degree below freezing unit. 55. Fish is laid out on portable shelves to be wheeled into cold-blow freezing rooms. 56. Plant employee Muller holds up yard-long black grouper in plant's 10 degree below zero storage room. 57. Six tons of fish can be frozen hourly in PCCA plant; frozen fish storage rooms have 400 ton capacity. 58. Vender using old-style delivery cart loads on milk at INLACA plant at 2 am. 59. INLACA repaired, cleaned and painted milk carts for improved sanitation and smoother running. 60. First model of new milk cart built by INLACA is filled with cartons of milk for inaugural delivery. 61. Day's milk supply is delivered to Italian bakery. 62. INLACA cartooned milk goes on sale in Chinese bar and restaurant in Valencia. 63. Customers purchase quart size INLACA milk from small Valencia store. 64. INLACA products are sold in stall in Valencia's public marketplace. 65. Public market milk stall is open for business each Saturday and Thursday morning. 66. Door delivery. 67. Doorstep delivery. 68. Window delivery. 69. Occupants of thatched hut receive morning milk supply from INLACA neighborhood vendor. 70. Paper carton facilitates handling by vendors. 71. Salesman makes rounds to homes located in prosperous Valencia residential district. 72. INLACA cartons become familiar sight on dinner table; above scene is taken at AIA staff house in Valencia.
    - VBEC, Monthly Progress Report, 11/15/1949, Prints: 26 (Box 15, Folder 262)
      73. Oil company executives board "autovia" for Valencia to visit AIA projects in that area and Chirgua farm. 74. At Chirgua machinery shed, Morrison Tucker shows oil company executives new equipment in use on farm. 75. "Todos" market, preparing for December opening, marks step forward in food retailing in Marcaibo. 76. From right: Diego Garcia, Frank Rothaug, "Todos" Directors; R.O. Provost, James O'Neill, Manager and Assistant. 77. "Todos," with 800 sq. meters open to public, will carry complete line foodstuffs and small household articles. 78. Prices stamped on all "Todos" articles build customer confidence and is convenient to buyers and employees. 79. River Guaire flood on Nov. 4 reached new "Frigorifica" warehouse nearing completion at San Martin, Caracas. 80. Employee points out waterline on "Frigorifica" warehouse after recession of River Guaire overflow. 81. Mud and silt covered floors inside warehouse. 82. Crews went to work immediately to remove rubbish and repair damage occasioned by flood. 83. New PACA manager, H.A. Von Wald and family arrive at Agua Blanca, which will serve as company headquarters. 84. Mechanical harvesting gets underway on Agua Blanca farm's 370 hectares of corn fields. 85. Wagonloads of corn move from fields 86. to grain processing site 87. where it is unloaded 88. for husking 89. and shelling. 90. This $118,300 installation allows complete mechanization of corn and rice operation at Agua Blanca farm. 91. Formerly fishermen took time out to clean 92. salt and dry excess catch. 93. PCCA plant now purchases excess catch 94. which is frozen and held for seasons of scarcity. 95. INLACA runs tests on ice cream manufacturing. 96. Ice cream cabinets are installed in INLACA plant. 97. Push carts are prepared for INLACA ice cream. 98. INLACA ice cream goes on sale at Valencia.
    - VBEC, Operations in Venezuela Report, 11/1949, Prints: 60 (Box 16, Folder 263)
      99. INLACA's hygienic paper milk cartons replacing glass bottles are already popular in public markets 100. and in "botiquines" - a handy Venezuelan combination lunchroom, bar and corner grocery. 101. INLACA makes 6 am milk delivery at thatched hut district 102. and urban homes to extend distribution to entire Venezuelan public and increase consumption of this basic food. 103. Milk delivery by burro is discouraged 104. in favor of sanitary, insulated street carts furnished to vendors by INLACA with free ice to conserve milk supply. 105. At its pasteurization plant in Valencia, INLACA is introducing modern milk industry techniques 106. such as Pure-Pak machine which automatically mounts, fills and seals milk cartons at rate of 35 per minute. 107. At La Guaira, Venezuela's main seaport, intermediary loads his cart with fish 108. to be sold off ice in open stalls at public market. 109. At same port, PCCA truck with ice supply takes on catch from company runboat to transport it 110. to PCCA retail store in Caracas which offers public a fresh product handled on ice from sea to customer. 111. Behind pier is PACA's new 16,400 square foot refrigeration, ice manufacturing and fish processing plant 112. which manufactures 30 tons of ice daily and has capacity to freeze 6,600 pounds of fish every 4 hours. 113. Puerto La Cruz fishermen tugged their boats up to theand waded to shore to purchase needed supplies 114. until PCCA constructed a 500 foot long pier where ice, fresh water and gasoline is available and fish can be sold. 115. Fishing without ice oftentimes meant spoiled catch, and forced fishermen to hurry back to shore 116. to market their catch while fresh and salt surplus. 117. installed ice boxes in boats and furnished free ice 118. constructing icing stations at strategic island points where fishermen can sell their entire catch and take on ice. 119. doubling production and income of Venezuelan fishermen. 120. Motors supplied by PCCA on easy terms 121. mean less sailing time and more fishing time 122. Central passageway in CADA's new Caracas warehouse opens into individual cold-storage compartments 123. equipped with built-in pulley system to allow easy transportation of meat and heavy produce within plant. 124. Final instructions are being made in second warehouse constructed by CADA in busy industrial area in south Caracas. 125. Customers took quickly to convenient self-service system 126. and approved CADA's method of displaying prices on all items, outdating local custom of grocery store haggling. 127. CADA's 60,000 sq. ft. warehouse in Maracaibo, large consuming center for west Venezuelan farm products, nears completion. 128. Typical Venezuelan corner grocery contrasts sharply 129. with modern food store opened by CADA in La Bandera, cross-roads of trade for large Caracas residential areas. 130. Workers' thatched huts were torn down by PACA 131. and replaced by clean, white bungalows with electricity and running water for more pleasant and healthful home life. 132. VBEC trainees work on PACA farms in program to encourage U.S. young men to meet challenge of rural Latin America. 133. Modern poultry installation on outskirts of Caracas produces 3,000 birds weekly for local convenience. 134. PACA flew in pure Duroc Jersey hogs as base of swine program to contribute to lowering meat shortages in Venezuela. 135. Only pure-bred St. Gertrudis herd in South American tropics - is developed on PACA's 8,000-acre ranch in West Venezuela. 136. PACA sells young cross-breeds produced on farms to local ranchers to stimulate top grade breeding programs in Venezuela. 137. Pure Zebu imported by PACA from Texas are being both reproduced and crossed with native cattle to improve local breeds. 138. By clearing stumps and brush from run-down pastures with bulldozers and Argentine rollers, and slight reseeding 139. PACA was able to double number of cattle carried on its 5500 acres of Para and Guinea grass. 140. Forty acres of unproductive plantain plants 141. were expanded into 750 acres of well-cultivated groves producing 2000 stems of this basic food weekly. 142. Slow task of picking corn by hand ties up valuable land 143. while mechanical corn harvesters free fields for double cropping on PACA farms. 144. Problem of hiring scarce farm hands to dig potatoes during harvest season was eliminated 145. with mechanical diggers which unearth 20 acres daily. 146. Effective use of insecticides can mean difference between success or complete loss of crop in tropical Venezuela. 147. PACA installed "rainmaker" irrigation to allow production to continue during 6 months' dry season. 148. Full day's work for farm laborers sowing corn by hand 149. is a one hour job for mechanical planters used by PACA. 150. Dish harrows 151. outdated "man with hoe". 152. Ox-drawn plows gave way to tractors on PACA farms 153. as U.S. farm technicians trained alert Venezuelan workers in competent handling of heavy farm machinery. 154. Sixteen ton bulldozers 155. replaced laborious "machete" clearing 156. back in 1948 when PACA deforested 2000 acres of Venezuelan land and put it in modern cultivation. 157. While Venezuelan government officials and Nelson Rockefeller meet to inaugurate new VBEC projects 158. the program is already beginning to touch many lives.
    - Via Lactea, General, Prints: 42 (Box 16, Folder 264)
      1. A conveyor belt placed on the platform of the "Via Lactea" carries raw milk from insulated trucks to the reception room for inspection and weighing. 2. Raw milk is delivered in special insulated trucks from Perija, about 80 miles from Maracaibo to the Via Lactea pasteurization plant. 3. Milk cartons are delivered to stores in handy, sanitary wire baskets. 4. "Via Lactea" trucks deliver cartons of fresh pasteurized milk for retailing in modern supermarkets. 5. The Shell Hospital in Bella Vista district Maracaibo, is one of Via Lactea's steady customers. 6. Via Lactea truck stationed at Punto Fijo picks up milk flown in from Maracaibo for delivery to oil camps throughout the Paraguana Peninsula. 7. Via Lactea milk plant illustrated at night. 8. The Via Lactea pasteurizing plant in Maracaibo has been visited recently by important members of the VE government. The sign says "For a Sound, Strong People". 9. Dr. Alipio Cuellar manager of the Via Lactea pasteurizing plant in Maracaibo, discusses the merits of the plant's product with Dr. Alberto Arvelo Torrealba, Minister of Agriculture, while Dr. Ramon Pinto Salvatierra, President of the National Agrarian Institute, inspects some of the plant equipment. 10. Dr. Alberto Arvelo Torrealba, Venezuelan Minister of Agriculture, talks milk with Via Lactea plant manager, Dr. Alipio Cuellar in Maracaibo. Dr. Ramon Pinto Salvatierri, President of the National Agrarian Institute looks over dome of the plant's modern equipment. 11. Via Lactea's young plant manager, Dr. Alipio Cuellar plays host at a milk party. Sampling the brew from right to left are Dr. Cuellar, Dr. Alberto Arvelo Torrealba, Sr. Urdaneta, Zulia State Minister of Agriculture, and Dr. Ramon Pinto Salvatierri, President of the National Agrarian Institute. 12. Via Lactea's young plant manager, Dr. Alipio Cuellar plays host at a milk party. Sampling the brew from right to left are Dr. Cuellar, Dr. Alberto Arvelo Torrealba, Sr. Urdaneta, Zulia State Minister of Agriculture, and Dr. Ramon Pinto Salvatierri, President of the National Agrarian Institute. 13. A pail of cool water is dumped into the warm cheese mixture to help it congeal, another in the complicated series of steps to turn out Italian style cheese at the Via Lactea plant in Maraciabo. 14. Via Lactea's cheese expert, who learned his trade in Italy, marks his product, one of the series of treatments which gives Via Lactea product of a flavor identical with that of more expensive cheeses. 15. As the cheese thickens rapidly, it is necessary for Via Lactea's cheese maker to stir it frequently. This tank full of cheese in the aging is being protected from foreign matter; in taste and quality it offers competition for imported cheeses and can be sold for less - another basic industry for Venezuela. 16. No caption. 17. The sweeper is collecting curds for cheese-making in Via Lactea's plant at Maracaibo. 18. Via Lactea's cheese expert fits curds into a frame for pressing cheese. 19. Via Lactea's new Italian type cheese is being pressed. 20. Via Lactea's cheese maker checks the temperature of his product. 21. Via Lactea employees are filling an open tank with liquid cheese, one of a variety being made for the first time in Venezuela by VBEC Maracaibo plant. 22. VBEC's daily engineers, Quentin Kubicek, checks on a preliminary operation in the complex process of pasteurizing milk. Kubicek, who visits both INLACA and Via Lactea, is shown at the Maracaibo plant. 23. Additional equipment to increase output of its popular pasteurized white cheese recently has been installed by Via Lactea, CA, western Venezuelan milk company of VBEC. 24. No caption. 25. Via Lactea distributor makes his morning rounds in Maracaibo. 26. Via Lactea distributor makes his morning rounds in Maracaibo. 27. Via Lactea (Milky way) is a landmark in the Maracaibo industrial suburb of Los Haticos. 28. A truck load of milk is arriving from the dairy lands of Zulia for pasteurization at VBEC's plant. 29. It's quite a reach to the carton of Via Lactea, but next year this school girl, who has been taught that milk is good for growth, will be able to make it without stretching. 30. Via Lactea distributors have lined up their trucks ready to load the morning's milk supply aboard. 31. Gladiolas and calla lilies are blooming in spring in front of the Via Lactea milk pasteurizing plant in Maracaibo. 32. Maracaibo health inspector (described by Via Lactea sales manager Geronimo Ugarte as "the toughest of all" tests Via Lactea milk in the plant laboratory. 33. Cheese is setting in the tank in the background of this photo taken by Paul Meyn of equipment at the Via Lactea plant in Maracaibo. 34. Clip, clip, clipand each of the thousands of paraffinated cardboard cartons is sealed hermetically, guaranteeing against any contamination or adulteration of Via Lactea pasteurized milk. As the cartons move through the aperture to the rear, they are placed in wooden carrier crates and put aboard the delivery trucks for distribution. 35. This is the assortment of products prepared at the Via Lactea plant in Maracaibo. The most recent addition to the lot is "Frosty", an ice cream introduced to Maracaibo by Gordon Coates, now sales manager for the Dairy Products Division of the VBEC. 36. Here is Via Lactea pasteurized milk with assortment of relatives in the background. 37. Via Lactea pasteurized milk is served at the exclusive new Hotel del Lago in Maracaibo. 38. An eager customer claims his carton of Via Lactea in one of the humble neighborhoods of Maracaibo. 39. A.F. Gonzalez, Via Lactea distributor, is on his morning rounds in Maracaibo. 40. Via Lactea pasteurized milk is featured at this roadside refreshment stand in Maracaibo. Here distributor A.F. Gonzolez delivers a four liter order. 41. Trusting customer buys a half liter of Via Lactea pasteurized milk for on-the-spot consumption. Health authorities are urging the substitution of wholesome pasteurized milk for soft drinks as casual refreshment. 42. Via Lactea delivery boy leaves two liters of pasteurized milk at this scarred doorway.
    - Via Lactea, General, Prints: 47 (Box 16, Folder 265)